Guide to the Wick Fowler Collection
The Wittliff Collections
Wick Fowler Collection
1944-1991
1944-1945
1965-1978
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Fowler, Wick (1909-1972)
SWWC.124
9.25 Linear Feet
7 boxes
Journalist and chili enthusiast Wick Fowler (1909-1972) was born Homer Thomas Wilson Fowler in Big Sandy, Texas and grew up in Victoria, Texas. The Wick Fowler papers span 1944-1991 (bulk dates: 1944-1945, 1965-1978) and document Fowler's journalism work as well as the Chili Appreciation Society International and Fowler's 2-Alarm Chili product.
Scope and Contents
The Wick Fowler papers span 1944-1991 (bulk dates: 1944-1945, 1965-1978) and document Fowler's journalism work as well as the Chili Appreciation Society International and Fowler's 2-Alarm Chili product. The collection is arranged in 7 series: Biographical Information, Writings, Chili, Correspondence, Audio Recordings, General Newspapers, and Printed Material.
The largest series, Chili, documents the chili cook-off in Terlingua, the Chili Appreciation Society International, and Wick Fowler's 2-Alarm Chili product, and contains articles and clippings, a scrapbook, promotional materials, photographic materials, and artifacts. Note that the while the scrapbook largely contains Chili-related clippings, awards, posters, advertisements, and a draft by Fowler, it also contains articles by Fowler on World War II, the Vietnam War, crime, and boating.
The second series, Writings, documents Fowler's career as a journalist. Subseries are World War II, Vietnam War, Humor, John Connally Assassination Attempt, Crime and Safety, and Boating. Each subseries contains clippings and columns by Fowler, including his "Vietnam Diary," a special insert for the Dallas Morning News on February 27, 1966. Other items of note include articles on journalist Ernie Pyle, clippings documenting Fowler's trip to Vietnam with Texas businessman H. Ross Perot, photographs of daily life in Vietnam and published photographs by Fowler. Also of note are two folders of notecards containing jokes, one-liners, and subject matter for speaking engagements.
The Correspondence series is also divided into periods, which are World War II, Vietnam, Chili, and family condolences. An exception to this is the Letters to Fowler, found in Writings-World War II, which includes hand-written and typed notes from various colleagues.
Many materials have been placed in oversized boxes. Researchers should note the box number on the container list as they are not always consecutive.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 7 series: Biographical Information, Writings, Chili, Correspondence, Audio Recordings, General Newspapers, and Printed Material.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gordon Fowler & Marcia Ball, 2016.
Biographical Note
Journalist and chili enthusiast Wick Fowler (1909-1972) was born Homer Thomas Wilson Fowler in Big Sandy, Texas and grew up in Victoria, Texas.
Fowler began his newspaper career at the Austin American Statesman, then joined the Dallas Morning News, and later became editor of the Midland Reporter Telegram. During World War II he served as the only Texas news correspondent, writing for the Dallas Morning News, and was awarded a Purple Heart after being wounded in Italy with fellow journalist Ernie Pyle. He followed the 36th Infantry Division, which was partially comprised of men from his former National Guard unit.
During the Vietnam War Fowler shipped out to Vietnam as a war correspondent for the Denton Record Chronicle. Again Fowler told the story of Texan soldiers. He returned later to cover the local boys for 15 Texas newspapers, and again with Texas businessman H. Ross Perot in attempts to return prisoners of war.
Fowler helped found the Chili Appreciation Society International and created Wick Fowler's 2-Alarm Chili product, both of which are still active. Both ideas were born of a chili cook-off first held in Terlingua, Texas in 1967, in which Fowler competed against Francis X. Tolbert, a friend and colleague at the Dallas Morning News.
Fowler was also a humorist, writing columns such as the "Towering Texan," "Fowler Fare," and "The World's Fare" from 1947-1968. He brought Wick Fowler's 2-Alarm Chili on his trips to Vietnam, and was called on to cheer the troops in World War II. Fowler also wrote on local issues such as the John F. Kennedy assassination in Dallas in which Texas governor John Connally was injured, crime and safety, and boating.
Sources:
Wood, Sam, "A tribute to Wick Fowler…," Texas State Directory, ca 1973, page 33.
Handbook of Texas Online, Alice M. Shukalo, "Fowler, Homer Thomas Wilson [Wick]," accessed August 18, 2016, http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/ffo50.
Index Terms
Subjects
Humor; World War, 1939-1945; Journalism; chili; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Chili con carne
Places
Texas -- Newspapers
- Biographical Information, 1944-1978
  Series Description
  Contains obituaries, newspaper articles on Fowler, and photographic materials.
  - Obituaries, 1972
    - Austin American (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Austin Statesman (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dallas Morning News (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Other newspapers (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Publications (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clippings scrapbook (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspapers, 1944-1979, undated
    - Sparks, 1944-1946, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Scope and Contents
      Dallas Morning News-WFAA-KGKO Employees Roundtable
    - Newspapers, 1944-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1944-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Small clippings, 1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Publications, 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Articles on family, 1946-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Dallas Morning News ad, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Political ads, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Press Club of Dallas documents, 1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Writings on Victoria, Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographic material, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    4 5x7 b&w prints, 8 8x10 b&w prints, 6 4x5 b&w prints, negatives, digital photographs-printouts available for access)
- Writings, 1944-1970
  The second series, Writings, documents Fowler's career as a journalist. Subseries are World War II, Vietnam War, Humor, John Connally Assassination Attempt, Crime and Safety, and Boating. Each subseries contains clippings and columns by Fowler, including his "Vietnam Diary," a special insert for the Dallas Morning News on February 27, 1966. Other items of note include articles on journalist Ernie Pyle, clippings documenting Fowler's trip to Vietnam with Texas businessman H. Ross Perot, photographs of daily life in Vietnam and published photographs by Fowler. Also of note are two folders of notecards containing jokes, one-liners, and subject matter for speaking engagements.
  - World War II, 1944-1945, undated
    - Notes, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Articles by Fowler, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Articles by Fowler (scrapbook), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Documents, 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Cartoons, military documents, war correspondents meeting documents
    - Ernie Pyle articles, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Tribute to Ernie Pyle" audio reel, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Articles by Fowler (oversized scrapbook), 1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Articles by Fowler (oversized), 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Articles by Fowler (oversized), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Fowler, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - General newspapers, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Vietnam War, 1965-1970
    - "Vietnam Diary", Dallas Morning News special insert, February 27, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Clippings by Fowler, 1966-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - General newspapers and maps, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Scenes of daily life, airplane; 17 3½ x 2 ½ b&w prints, 2 5x7 b&w prints
    - Newspaper photographs by Fowler, 1966-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Clippings on Fowler, 1966, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Clippings on Ross Perot, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Fowler event schedules, 1966, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Humor, 1947, 1963-1971
    - Notecards, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
    - "Towering Texan" column, February 1947 - April 1947 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Fowler Fare" column, 1963-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "The World's Fare" column, 1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
    - Other columns, 1963, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Oversized columns, 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Star Bright" column, 1971 (Box 3, Box 10)
      Austin American-Statesman insert
  - John Connally assassination attempt, 1963-1965
    - Articles by Fowler, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - General articles, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Notes and inauguration invitation, 1963, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Other writings, 1963-1969
    - Crime and Safety, 1968-1969, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Speech, clippings, documents, political ad.
    - Boating article by Fowler, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Chili, 1964-1982
  The largest series, Chili, documents the chili cook-off in Terlingua, the Chili Appreciation Society International, and Wick Fowler's 2-Alarm Chili product, and contains articles and clippings, a scrapbook, promotional materials, photographic materials, and artifacts. Note that the while the scrapbook largely contains Chili-related clippings, awards, posters, advertisements, and a draft by Fowler, it also contains articles by Fowler on World War II, the Vietnam War, crime, and boating.
  - Articles, 1945, 1964-1982
    - Magazine articles, 1967-1968, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Clippings (large), 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Clippings (large), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Clippings, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Clippings (large), 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Clippings, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Clippings (large), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Clippings, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Clippings (large), 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1945, 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes chili clippings, award, posters, advertisements, draft by Fowler; and Fowler articles on World War II, Vietnam War, crime, boating.
  - Promotion, 1962, 1981, undated
    - Tabloid and broadsheets, 1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Poster, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Poster, 1981 (Map-case Dr. 9)
  - Photographic material, circa 1960-1971
    - (7) 8x10 b&w prints, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - (40) 3.5x3.5 and 3.5 x 4.5 b&w and color prints, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Terlingua 1968", circa 1967, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      (93) 3.5x3.5 prints
    - "Terlingua 1969" negatives, circa 1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "Terlingua Nov. 71" negatives, circa 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Artifacts, 1968-1975, undated
    - Documents (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Press release, proclamation, speech
    - Printed materials, 1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Business cards, cooking guide, label, letterhead
    - "Wick Fowler's Famous 2-alarm Chili" packaging, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Bumper stickers (2), 1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - "Mis amigos hambrientos" cookbook by Allegani Jani Schofield, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Includes memory of Fowler, page 22
- Correspondence, 1944-1946, 1965-1980, undated
  The Correspondence series is divided into periods, which are World War II, Vietnam, Chili, and family condolences. An exception to this is the Letters to Fowler, found in Writings-World War II, which includes hand-written and typed notes from various colleagues.
  - World War II correspondence, 1944-1946, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam War correspondence, 1965-1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chili correspondence, 1967-1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Condolences to Fowler family, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Various, 1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Envelopes, 1945-1970 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Audio Recordings, 1967-1970, undated
  ¼ inch reel-to-reel tapes
  - "#1", undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "McDonalds", January 1970 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Barbershop", November 12, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Unlabeled, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Unlabeled, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
- General Newspapers, 1966-1974, 1991
  Various clippings and newspapers collected by Fowler.
  - Clippings, 1966-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers, 1967-1974, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Victoria Advocate, Historical Edition, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Printed Material, 1952, undated
  - Humorous dollar bill; Headliners Club seal, 1952; undated (Box 7, Folder 4)